ada.org 2018-12-27

# Privacy Policy

  * ADA Contact Information
  * How We May Use and Disclose Information We Collect About You 
  * Your Rights and Responsibilities
  * Children’s Privacy
  * More About Our Privacy Practices
  * Changes, Comments and Questions
  * ADA® credentialing service, powered by CAQH ProView®
  * ADA Communities™ online member forums

**Last Updated:   November 29, 2018  
**

This Privacy Notice explains how the American Dental Association (“ADA”) and its subsidiaries, charities and affiliated entities (collectively, “ADA,” “we," “us” or “our”) collect information about you through our website and how this information is then used or disclosed. This Privacy Notice does not apply to websites that do not display or link to this notice or that have their own privacy notices or to information we may collect from you or about you in other ways, including through emails you may send to us.

### ADA Contact Information

You may contact us about this Privacy Notice:

Via postal address:  
American Dental Association  
Attn: General Counsel  
211 E. Chicago Ave.  
Chicago, IL 60611  
By email [MSC@ada.org](mailto:MSC@ada.org)

### How We May Use and Disclose Information We Collect About You

The information we collect via our website may be used and disclosed to improve the content of ADA.org and advance the ADA’s mission. For example, the ADA may use this information for purposes such as:

  * Registering you for, or providing you with information, programs and services you have requested

  * Processing, fulfilling and following up on your orders or membership application

  * Providing access to publications

  * Responding to your emails or online requests

  * Sending you information you request

  * Sending and processing surveys and continuing education quizzes

  * Publishing membership directories and registration lists

  * Sharing with companies to offer you products and services that may be of interest to you 

  * Sharing your email address with companies to deliver communications on our behalf

  * Sharing information about you with members and state and local dental societies

  * Sharing information about you with service providers, vendors and other companies we do business with

  * Sharing with third parties as required by law

  * Sharing demographic information for research purposes

  * Sharing your email address as described below

We collect information such as the internet protocol (IP) address of visitors to our website, aggregate information on what pages users access or visit, user-specific information on what pages users access or visit, and information volunteered by users, including from surveys, purchases and/or registrations. We may collect information about visitors to our website to help measure the effectiveness of advertising campaigns. We also may collect the email addresses of those who communicate with us via email. Our system can recognize the identity of individuals who sign in using their usernames and passwords.

With respect to cookies: We use cookies for a number of purposes, including to administer our website and to record session information, such as items that users add to their shopping carts and user-specific information on what pages users access or visit.

Advertising on ADA.org may be served through a vendor that uses IP addresses for purposes such as controlling ad frequency.

The ADA, its subsidiaries, charities, and affiliates may use or disclose individual's contact information and other information about you, such as your occupation, specialty, member status, graduation date and dental school, to alert you to new information, products and services, events and other opportunities. From time to time, we may also make your contact information and other information about you available to other organizations we believe to be reputable, such as companies whose products or services we think you might find interesting. If you register on ADA.org to attend an event, the ADA may provide an attendee list to other attendees and to entities that collaborate with the ADA on the event.

With respect to email addresses: We generally do not knowingly disclose an individual's e-mail address without the individual's express or implied consent outside the ADA, its service providers, subsidiaries and affiliated entities, ADA members, and state and local dental societies. However, we may disclose your e-mail address in certain situations; for example, if you serve in a leadership capacity or if you provide your e-mail address in connection with an event or an attendee list.

The ADA maintains directories of dentists that may include information you submit via our website. These directories are shared with ADA members and state and local dental societies. A directory containing information about ADA members is publicly accessible on MouthHealthy.org; members may elect to provide additional information, such as email address and photo, through the expanded profile option.

The ADA uses an association management database to collect, maintain, use, and share information about member and nonmember dentists who have attended a U.S. dental school, as well as individuals who interact with the ADA. Information in the database is generally accessible to state and local dental societies of the ADA “tripartite.” A “person record” may be created in the database for such dentists and other individuals. For example, a person record may be created when a dentist or other individual interacts with the ADA by becoming a member, purchasing an item or service, attending a meeting, volunteering, attending a continuing education or other course, or communicating with the ADA. 

A person record contains information about the individual such as name, contact information, demographics, membership history, a record of purchases and meetings attended, volunteer positions held, and communications with the ADA and state and local dental societies.

Person records are retained indefinitely. ADA may use a person record for any permissible purpose under the applicable privacy notice. ADA has entered into agreements with participating state and local dental societies of the ADA tripartite that permit the society to use a person record for any permissible purpose if the individual is eligible for membership in the society; however, if the individual is not eligible for membership in the society, the society may use the person record only for registration of the individual at society sponsored meetings, for determining dues owed, for updating the data (e.g., with correct contact information), to assist with order fulfillment, to create de-identified aggregated data solely for internal use, and for any other purpose for which the ADA has provided express written permission. Person records may not be used or disclosed in a way that would violate this ADA.org Privacy Notice.

The ADA may provide delegates’ names and mailing addresses in response to a request from a dental specialty organization. The Journal of the American Dental Association (JADA) publishes delegates’ names, districts, cities and states, as well as information, including ADA.org email addresses, about officers and trustees.

The ADA may share or license information about you to a third party if, in our sole discretion, we believe that it is (1) reasonably necessary to perform a service or deliver a product or publication; (2) authorized by you or as set forth in any applicable agreement (whether express or implied) between you and ADA, or with your consent; (3) permitted under this Privacy Notice; (4) required by statute or regulation; (5) of interest to dentists, dental students, members of the dental team, or consumers of dental services, or (6) in the good-faith belief that such action is appropriate for reasons of security or legal compliance.

If you participate in an activity such as attending or speaking at a program or authoring a publication, information such as your name and photo may be shared via ADA.org or ADA publications.

The ADA also occasionally hires other individuals and entities to provide services on our behalf, including, but not limited to, hosting of online resources, processing credit card transactions, packaging, order fulfillment, answering customer questions about products or services, consulting services, data modeling, printing, sending postal mail and processing membership and event registration. We will provide those companies with information they need to deliver the service. Third parties may collect information such as your IP address that may indicate your online activities over time or across different websites when you use our websites. At this time, this website does not respond to do-not-track signals.

Certain sensitive personal information is protected by security measures (that may include computer safeguards and secured files and buildings security) to protect the information from unauthorized access and use. If such information is disposed of, it will be done securely.

### ADA® credentialing service, powered by CAQH ProView®

If you use the ADA® credentialing service, powered by CAQH ProView®, you consent to and authorize the ADA’s transfer of certain information about you to CAQH ProView® to use in accordance with the Council for Affordable Quality Healthcare, Inc. (“CAQH”) applicable terms of use and privacy policy To the extent you designate ADA to receive information about you from CAQH (including its service providers), the ADA may use the information about you in accordance with ADA’s applicable Terms of Use and Privacy Notice, or upon your consent.

### Your Rights and Responsibilities

It is important when you wish to exercise your rights that you contact us via any of the means listed in the first section of this Privacy Notice.

While the ADA takes measures to protect your personal information, no security measure or network is entirely secure. Your password to access ADA.org should be complex and should never be shared with anyone, and should be changed from time to time. After you access ADA.org, you should log off and exit your browser so unauthorized persons cannot access the site.

If you do not want to receive postal mail, telephone calls from us in the future, or if you do not want us to share your contact information in the manner described above, please provide us with your exact name and postal addresses, phone and fax numbers and, if appropriate, ADA membership number to [msc@ada.org](mailto:msc@ada.org). It may take up to four weeks for your opt out to become effective. While we will continue to share information we maintain about you with our service providers, subsidiary and affiliates, and with state and local dental societies, we will take reasonable steps to ensure that any other specific contact information you so identify is removed from lists we share with other organizations. We have instituted opt-out capabilities to help you avoid receiving unwanted commercial email messages from the ADA. ADA will honor such requests within ten business days.

On request we may provide you with access to information that you submitted via ADA.org, such as certain transaction information (e.g., dates on which you made purchases, amounts and types of purchases), communications that you have directed to our site (e.g., emails, user inquiries), and contact information (e.g., name, address, phone number).

On request we may also offer the ability to have inaccuracies corrected in contact information, financial information, unique identifiers, transaction information and certain other data.

In addition to the other rights we note in this Privacy Notice, you also have the right to contact the ADA to obtain the following information:

1\. What personal information about you the ADA holds;

2\. For what purposes does ADA process your information;

3\. To what third parties (and in what jurisdictions) has or may the ADA disclose your personal information;

4\. How long will your data be maintained by the ADA (and how that period of time has been calculated);

5\. How to request correction or deletion of specific portions of your personal data held by the ADA that you believe are incorrect; and

6\. The source(s) from which the ADA has obtained your personal data.

You may also contact us at [msc@ada.org](mailto:msc@ada.org) if you believe your information is being used improperly.

You may provide consent to additional uses and disclosures; for example, in connection with a product or service offered by the ADA, an affiliated entity, or a third party.

### Children's Privacy

We do not knowingly solicit data online from, or market online to children under the age of 13.

### More About Our Privacy Practices 

With respect to other websites and servers: ADA.org contains links to other websites. We have no control over and take no responsibility for the privacy practices or content of those sites.

We use Doubleclick for Publishers (DFP) Small Business to serve ads on our site. 

When users choose to make payments via credit cards, they do so on the website of a third party service provider. We do not store or reuse credit card information unless you have given us your credit card information directly and authorized us to do so. 

### Changes, Comments and Questions 

If our Privacy Notice changes at some time in the future we will post the revised Privacy Notice to our website to notify you, and those changes will be effective on the day that we post the revised privacy notice. The latest version of our Privacy Notice will always be available at ADA.org.

We welcome your comments or questions about our Privacy Notice and privacy practices. If you feel that this site is not following its stated policy, please let us know.

### ADA Communities™ online member forums

If you use ADA Communities, the following provisions apply, in addition to the other provisions of the ADA.org Privacy Notice.

ADA Communities is a digital platform where ADA member dentists, staff members of ADA and state and local dental societies, and others can connect and converse on professional, clinical and personal interests, through a social media interface.  

The following information applies to personal information that ADA collects from users of ADA Communities. In this section, a “user” includes any individual who creates an ADA Communities account, as well as others who have access to ADA Communities, such as employees and independent contractors of ADA and its affiliates, state and local dental associations, and certain service providers and other third parties. For purposes of this section, “affiliate” means an ADA subsidiary or charity, such as ADA Business Enterprises, Inc. (“ADABEI”) and the ADA Foundation.

This ADA Communities section of the Privacy Notice provides information about the personal information that American Dental Association (“ADA”) collects from users of ADA Communities, and how that information is used and shared. 

The ADA websites and platform are directed towards users who reside in the United States of America only.  It is not our intent or purpose to gather personally identifiable information from individuals residing outside the U.S. **_You consent and acknowledge that anything you post or provide on or via ADA Communities, including but not limited to your personal information, may be transferred to, maintained, and processed in the United States in accordance with the applicable Terms of Use and Privacy Notice._**

If you have questions or concerns of a technical nature about ADA Communities, contact:

AMERICAN DENTAL ASSOCIATION  
Technical Support Center  
211 E. Chicago Ave.  
Chicago, IL 60611  
312.440.7700

If you have questions or concerns about ADA Communities or this ADA Communities Privacy Notice, or about any post, content, or particular group on ADA Communities or if you would like to get in touch with us concerning ADA Communities for any other reason, please contact:

AMERICAN DENTAL ASSOCIATION  
Member Service Center  
211 E. Chicago Avenue  
Chicago, IL 60611  
800.621.8099

If you wish to delete your ADA Communities account, email [support@rasa.io](mailto:support@rasa.io?subject=inquiry%20from%20the%20Privacy%20Notice) or contact ADA via the support icon within the system. 

**I. What personal information does ADA collect on ADA Communities?**

ADA collects information, such as text, posts, links, images, video, messages and other communications, and other data that users create, post, share and provide on ADA Communities, and information about things that users do on ADA Communities. Such information may be combined with other information that ADA has about users. For example, ADA collects:  
**_  
Information users provide._** ADA collects the content and other information, such as the information listed above, that users create, post, share and provide on ADA Communities. 

**_Information about, or incorporated in, other information._** ADA collects information that may be incorporated in other information; for example, if a user posts a photo, ADA may collect where and when the photo was taken. ADA collects information about other information, such as the date a file is created. ADA also collects information about users that is created or generated by other users.

**_Information about what users do._** ADA also collects information about things users do on ADA Communities. For example, ADA collects information such as the date a user signs up for ADA Communities, the kinds of content a user views or engages with, how long and often a user is active in ADA Communities, and things a user does on ADA Communities, such as sending messages to other users, or posting information about other users.

**_Information about groups and connections._** ADA collects information about users’ groups and connections, such as the groups a user creates or joins, which other users a user is connected to and how they interact with each other, the groups a user is most likely to share with, and the other users a user communicates with. ADA may also collect contact information from users through ADA Communities.

**_Information from other websites you visit._** For example, ADA may have access to information about websites that users visited prior to coming to ADA Communities. If a user uses the same email address to sign up for ADA Communities and another social media platform powered by the same service provider, ADA may collect and aggregate information based on the information the user provides and things the user does on both platforms. The service provider may also collect and aggregate information based on the information the user provides and things the user does on both websites, and make the information available to the controller of the other platform.

**_Information about users’ devices._** ADA may collect information about the devices used to access ADA Communities, such as computers and phones, and may associate such information to provide consistent service across a user’s devices. Here are some examples of such information:

  * Attributes such as the operating system, hardware version, device settings, file and software names and types, battery and signal strength, and device identifiers.

  * Device locations, including specific geographic locations, such as through GPS, Bluetooth, or WiFi signals.

  * Connection information such as the name of users’ mobile operator or ISP, browser type, language and time zone, mobile phone number and IP address.

  * Information from third parties. ADA receives information about users and their activities on and off ADA Communities from third-parties, such as information from a third party when ADA and the third party jointly offer services, or from an advertiser about a user’s experiences or interactions with the third party or advertiser. 

  * ADA affiliates and state and local dental associations. ADA receives information about users from ADA affiliates, from state and local dental associations, and from other sources. 

**II. How does ADA use the information it collects on ADA Communities?**

ADA uses information that it collects on ADA Communities to help provide and support ADA Communities and other ADA services, to help achieve ADA’s mission, and to help ADA conduct and provide other products, projects, messages, events, initiatives, and for any other lawful purpose. ADA also provides such information to ADA affiliates and state and local dental associations to help them achieve their missions, and to help them conduct and provide their products, projects and initiatives. ADA may combine information that it collects on ADA Communities with information that ADA and others collect elsewhere, such as information ADA collects on ADA.org. 

For example, ADA and its affiliates may use information collected on ADA Communities to: 

  * Develop, provide and improve ADA Communities and other products, services, projects and initiatives, both on and off ADA Communities. 

  * Deliver ADA Communities, personalize content, and make suggestions for users by using information about users and others to understand how users use and interact with ADA Communities and the people, groups, ideas and things users are connected to and interested in on and off ADA Communities. 

  * Provide shortcuts and suggestions to users. For example, ADA may be able to suggest that a user connect with another user by comparing information a user provides to information ADA has about another user. 

  * If users provide location information about themselves or others, either directly or indirectly (e.g. such as location information provided as part of a photo), ADA and its affiliates may use such information (e.g., for tailoring ADA Communities for a user and others, helping a user find local events or offers in the area or to tell other users that a user is nearby). 

  * Conduct surveys and research, test features in development, analyze the information to evaluate and improve products and services, develop new products or features, and conduct audits and troubleshooting activities.

  * Send information such as marketing communications, communicate with users about ADA Communities and other products, services and initiatives

  * Let users know about ADA’s policies and terms, such as changes to Privacy Notices and Terms of Use. ADA also uses users’ information to respond when users contact ADA.

  * Show and measure ads and services. For example, ADA uses the information that ADA has to improve advertising and measurement systems so ADA can show individuals relevant ads on and off ADA Communities and measure the effectiveness and reach of ads and services. 

  * Promote safety and security; for example, by using information to help verify accounts and activity, and to promote safety and security on and off of ADA Communities, such as by investigating suspicious activity or violations of ADA’s terms or policies. 

State and local dental associations may also use information collected on ADA Communities. For example, they may use it to:

  * Develop, provide and improve their products, services, projects and initiatives. 

  * Personalize content, and make suggestions for users. 

  * Provide shortcuts and suggestions to users.

  * If users provide location information about themselves or others, use such information for purposes such as helping a user find local events or offers in the area or tell connections that a user is nearby. 

  * Send information such as marketing communications, communicate with users about ADA Communities and other products, services and initiatives.

ADA uses cookies and similar technologies to provide and support ADA Communities and other ADA services, and uses outlined and described in the Privacy Notice. 

**III. How is this information shared?**

ADA member dentists may use ADA Communities to connect and share with others, such as other member dentists and the staff of ADA, affiliates, and state and local dental associations. ADA makes this possible by sharing users’ information in various ways, such as the following:

> When users share and communicate using ADA Communities they may choose which group to post to, such as an open or closed group. Likewise, when a user sends a message to another user or users, the sender chooses the recipient(s). Although ADA does not monitor all activity on ADA Communities, ADA may be able to access information on ADA Communities, including but not limited to text, posts, links, images, video, content,  messages and communications (including those that have been deleted), as well as information about things user do on ADA Communities, including those in open groups and in closed groups.  
> 
> “Public ADA engagement data” is any information a user shares with all users of ADA Communities such as text based forum posts, images, links to articles and other information users choose to share in the groups, as well as information in users’ Profiles, and content users share on certain other public forums in ADA Communities. Public ADA Communities information is available to all users of ADA Communities and on certain other ADA services and databases.
> 
> Other users of ADA Communities may download or re-share content on and off ADA Communities, such as by copying content and making the content public on the Internet. When a user comments on another user’s post or “Upvotes” their content on ADA Communities, if their audience is public, the comment or “Upvote” will also be public to members of ADA Communities. Various people will see content others share about a user. Other users may share information about users on ADA Communities with the audience they choose, on or off ADA Communities. For example, a user may share a photo of a user, mention a user at a location in a post, or share information about a user that the user shared with them. 

_Apps, websites and third-party integrations on or using ADA Communities._ When a user uses a third-party app, website or other service that uses, or is integrated with, ADA Communities, the app, website or other service may receive information the user provides, or information about what the user does. For example, when a user engages in discussion with another user or users on ADA Communities, or uses the “Comment,” “Upvote,” or “Share” buttons, the website, app, or service (e.g., the program platform) may get information about the user’s activities or receive a comment or link that the user shares from the website on ADA Communities. In addition, when a user downloads or uses such third-party services, the third-party service can access the user’s Public Profile, which includes the user’s username or user ID, age range and country/language, list of connections, as well as any information that the user shares with them. 

_New owner or service provider._ If the ownership or control of all or part of ADA Communities or its assets changes, ADA may transfer users’ information to the new owner. ADA may also transfer users’ information to new service providers.

**_Sharing With Third Parties_**

ADA works with third parties who help ADA provide and improve ADA Communities and other services, or who use or offer advertising or related products, which helps makes it possible to operate ADA Communities and other ADA services and initiatives. 

Here are examples of the types of third parties with whom ADA and its affiliates may share information about users. State and local dental societies may also use such data to inform programs with third parties, such as advertisers or sponsors.

  * Advertising, Measurement and Analytics Services. To help make advertising and other messaging relevant and interesting, ADA, its affiliates, and state and local dental associations may use, and provide to advertising, measurement and analytics services entities for their use, information about users; for example, to make decisions concerning ads and messaging. Advertising, measurement and analytics services may provide or be provided information about the reach and effectiveness of advertising and messaging. In some cases the information may be de-identified or aggregated so it does not personally identify a user. For example, ADA may tell an advertiser how its ads performed, or how many people viewed their ads or installed an app after seeing an ad, or provide personally identifying or non-personally identifying demographic information to help the advertiser understand its audience or customers. 

  * Vendors, service providers and other entities. ADA, its affiliates and state and local dental associations may transfer user information to vendors, service providers, and others who support their missions, products, services and initiatives, such as providing technical infrastructure services, analyzing how products and services are used, measuring the effectiveness of ads and services, providing member services, facilitating payments, or conducting research and surveys. 

**IV. How can users manage or delete information about themselves?**

ADA stores data and makes it available as provided in the applicable Privacy Notice for as long as it is necessary (for example, to be able to provide products and services to users and others, including those described herein). Information associated with a user’s account may be kept until the account is deleted, unless the data is no longer needed (for example, to provide products and services). 

A user may delete his or her account any time. When a user deletes his or her account, the things the user posted, such as comments and photos, will no longer be visible on ADA Communities. If a user does not want to delete his or her account, but wants to temporarily stop using ADA Communities, the user may deactivate the account instead. If a user deletes his or her account, keep in mind that information that others have shared about the user is not part of the account and will not be deleted. 

If a user deletes information, such as a post, or deletes his or her account, ADA may continue to maintain the post, account, or other information even if it is no longer visible on ADA Communities. 

**V. How does ADA respond to legal requests or prevent harm?**

ADA may access, preserve and share a user’s information in response to a legal request (such as a search warrant, court order or subpoena) if ADA has a good faith belief doing so is required by law or would help protect ADA or an individual or entity from legal, reputational, financial, physical, or any other harm. ADA may also access, preserve and share information when ADA has a good faith belief it is necessary or appropriate to do so; for example, in order to: 

  * detect, prevent and address potential fraud and other illegal activity 
  * protect the Association, its affiliates, state and local dental societies, users and others, including as part of investigations 
  * help prevent death or imminent bodily harm. 

For example, ADA may provide information to third parties about a user’s account to prevent potential fraud and abuse or a potential antitrust violation on and off of ADA Communities. Information ADA has and receives about users, including financial transaction data related to purchases made, may be accessed, processed and retained for an extended period of time when it is the subject of a legal request or obligation, governmental investigation, or investigations concerning possible violations of ADA’s terms or policies, or otherwise to prevent harm. ADA also may retain information from posts and content or accounts disabled or deleted for any reason, such as violations of ADA terms, to prevent repeat abuse or other violations of ADA’s terms or to prevent other harms, or to comply with laws and legal requests. 

**VI. How will ADA notify users of changes to this ADA Communities Privacy Notice?**

ADA will notify users before making changes to this ADA Communities section of the Privacy Notice and give users the opportunity to review the revised Privacy Notice before continuing to use ADA Communities.
